We'll be right back.
I'm also in shock that it's here already.
So if we haven't met yet, my name is Ryan.
I have the privilege of being one of the pastors here.
And we are excited to turn our attention to Advent this season as we prepare to celebrate Christmas.
Now, if you didn't grow up in a church that celebrated Advent, that's okay.
I didn't really either.
But many churches throughout the world participate in a planned calendar.
I grew up in a Baptist church.
We didn't do this.
I didn't even really know this existed.
I'm sure some of you grew up in churches that had regular calendars so that much of the church throughout the world can be focused on the same passages, the same themes all throughout the year.
And although our church isn't a part of that tradition, I have come personally, and because I get to pick the calendar, you all have also come personally, corporately, to value two of the primary seasons in the church calendar, the season of Lent and the season of Advent.
And the reason that these two seasons in particular grab my attention is because they focus on the central themes of the biblical narrative, the coming of Jesus, the death, burial, and resurrection of Jesus, and ultimately the promise of the coming again of Jesus.
Lent is the season of preparation as we celebrate Christ's victory over death and the grave on Easter.
And I don't know about you, but I feel like that just happened a month or two ago.
But it did not.
It happened a while ago.
And again, the seasons remind us of how fast life can be.
The seasons remind us of how God works in the midst of our lives, no matter how busy they might be.
Lent is the season of preparation for the celebration of Christ's victory over death and the grave on Easter.
Advent is the time that we reflect.
We look back to the first coming of Jesus, the birth of Jesus.
But ultimately, Advent isn't just about looking backwards to the first coming of Jesus.
It's about looking forward with hope and with anticipation to the second coming of Jesus.
We, as American Christians, I don't know about you, but think about the songs we sing, the things that we think about at Advent, tend to primarily focus on looking back to the birth of Jesus.
But Advent is twofold.
It is about looking back to the birth of Jesus and forward to the second coming of Jesus.
Advent comes from a Latin word that simply means to come.
I'm a scholar now.
Did you guys know that?
At Advent, we remind ourselves that God was faithful to fulfill many of his promises through the birth and life of Jesus.
Therefore, because of that, because God was faithful to do what he promised to Israel to do through Jesus, we can be confident that what he has promised to do to the church in the future, he will do.
We can have confidence that God will faithfully fulfill his future promises.
Another beautiful thing about Advent that I've learned recently, and many of you probably already knew this.
I hadn't put two and two together, but Advent was intentionally placed near the winter solstice, not because this is when the early church fathers thought that Jesus was born, but because it's the darkest time of the year.
This intentionally reminds us that the world is not as it should be, that there is darkness where there was intended to be light.
But at Advent, we look back to Jesus, the light of the world, and we remind ourselves that in the midst of the darkest times, Jesus has brought forth his light.
And because he did that in the past, we can be confident that he will do that in the future.
One of my favorite promises for the future of Christ's coming is that the sun will be no more, that the presence of Christ will replace the sun, that he is the light of the world.
We see it dimly now, but we will see it completely in the future.
And that is what this Advent wreath is all about.
At Advent, we light candles to remind ourselves that the light of the world has come, but that light is still dim, and we are looking forward to a time when we will see it completely and fully.
And so I think I have a slide for this.
My main theme for you all to think about throughout the season of Advent is this.
At Advent, we look backwards with gratitude, and we look forward with anticipation.
May we do both of those things this season, not just one or the other.
May we look back to the coming of Jesus with gratitude and look forward to the second coming of Jesus with anticipation.
And if you grew up in a church that celebrated Advent year over year over year, you know how it works, right?
Hope, love, joy, peace.
We look at these things, and we remind ourselves that Jesus has come, and he has brought elements of hope, love, joy, and peace.
But ultimately, at his second coming, all of those things will be seen clearly and fully.
And we talked about last week, the reason I think that sometimes participating in these regular rhythms of the church calendar is so important is because for Christians in the American church, we talked about this last week, we love to focus on learning new information.
But I think oftentimes we just need to be reminded of the things that we already know to be true and put those things into practice.
How often are we filling our mind with new information and not living in the information that we already know?
Advent is about reminding ourselves that Christ is our hope, that Christ defines love for us, that he brings us joy and peace in the midst of chaotic circumstances.
And not just information that we know, but information that we live into.
So I think it's good that we remind ourselves of these things on a regular basis, not just so that we know them intellectually, but so that we hold ourselves accountable to live into them consistently.
So today, we light the candle of hope.
And last year, to be honest with you guys, I got some judgment from some of you for lighting the candles with a cigar torch.
But those of you that judged me for lighting the candles with a cigar torch have never felt the anxiety of trying to click the Bic lighter five or six times and not get it to light.
Like, you don't know the anxiety.
So don't judge me for using my cigar torch because it will work the first time or the second.
So today, we look, we focus our eyes on the hope that Jesus has brought.
Let's pray.
Father in heaven, we thank you.
We thank you that we have the opportunity to set aside just a little bit of time in this chaotic season to look back to the coming of Jesus.
The light of the world, who has brought us the first fruits of hope of the resurrection of Christ.
God, today, may we get a glimpse of that hope, not just intellectually, but in our souls, in our bodies, in our whole selves.
May we think about what this hope means for us in the midst of whatever difficult circumstances we might be facing.
God, I know there are people in here that are holding on to their last strand of hope.
May this morning you breathe a fresh wind of hope into their lives.
God, and for those of us that haven't yet faced the difficult circumstances of life that will hit all of us from time to time, may we bury this hope deep down in our souls so that when that difficult season comes, we have something to cling to, something to root ourselves in.
Lord, teach us to be a people of hope this morning, for your glory, for our good, and for the good of our neighbor.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
If you want to follow along with me, we're going to be in Luke chapter 1 this morning.
For most of our time, we'll hop over to 1 Corinthians 15.
If you want to mark both places, then you'll know where to go.
And if not, the words will be on the screen.
I'd love for you to do me a favor.
Raise your hand if you've ever met a famous person.
Anybody in here met famous?
Okay, a lot of us.
Now, here's the kicker.
Yell it out if you think the famous person you met is the most famous person represented in the room.
Robert De Niro, Dan Aykroyd, George Bush.
Those are three pretty good ones.
Now, let's vote on who's...
No, I'm just kidding.
I think a sitting president probably has some significant celebrity power.
I was trying to think about any famous people that I've met.
I haven't really had any awesome encounters with some famous people.
But a few weeks ago, our beloved worship leader and youth pastor, Donovan Russell, came back from California.
And he told me about a fun encounter that he had with a, what I would call is a C-level famous person.
Donovan ran into the actor that played the warden in Shawshank Redemption.
I don't even know his name.
That's how not famous he is to me.
I love Shawshank Redemption.
He's a fantastic actor.
But, I mean, C-level at best, right?
And so he's telling us this story about how his palms are getting sweaty, his knees are getting shaky.
Emily's trying to talk him into not going up to this guy and making a fool out of himself.
But, you know, you're in California.
You get the opportunity to meet a famous person.
And so Donovan makes his way to this guy outside the restaurant.
And Donovan's like, you wouldn't believe how badly I embarrassed myself.
You wouldn't believe it.
And he recounts the story.
And I'll let him, if you're really interested in the details of the story, be sure to hit Donovan up for that story.
But the reason I share this is because I think many of us, no matter how famous the person that we met was,
we felt this experience where we look at people who are, like, famous, and they just don't feel human to us.
They feel totally different than us.
And so it's hard to even relate to these people who have had these experiences of fame.
The reason I share this story is because I think we have the tendency to do the same thing with famous biblical characters in familiar biblical stories.
We tend to look at these people in the pages of Scripture and think of them as so other than human that we cannot even begin to relate to the experiences that they had.
But my argument this morning is that the pages of Scripture are actually filled with God using real people with real lives to do amazing things through the power of the Holy Spirit.
The people that we're reading about in the pages of Scripture are not superhuman or other than.
They are regular people with difficult, challenging lives.
And the Holy Spirit just happens to break into their story and invite them to participate in something incredible.
And my point here for all of us this morning is that what if we're missing out on some of the things that God might want for us
because we've read these pages of Scripture in such a way that we cannot relate to the stories that we're dealing with?
What if, like many of the characters in the Bible, God wants to use us to do things that we can never even imagine?
This morning I want to look at a familiar Christmas passage with the famous biblical character
and see if we can't relate to what she experienced in this story, specifically around the idea of hope.
So, Luke chapter 1, starting in verse 26, most of us will probably be familiar with this even if we didn't grow up in church.
It says this,
In the sixth month of Elizabeth's pregnancy, God sent the angel Gabriel to Nazareth, a village in Galilee.
A village, save that for later, to a virgin named Mary.
She was engaged to be married to a man named Joseph, a descendant of King David.
Gabriel appeared to her and he said,
Greetings, favored woman.
The Lord is with you.
Confused and disturbed, Mary tried to think what the angel could mean.
Don't be afraid, Mary, the angel told her, for you have found favor with God.
You will conceive and give birth to a son and you will name him Jesus.
He will be very great and he will be called the Son of the Most High.
The Lord will give him the throne of his ancestor David and he will reign over Israel forever and his kingdom will never end.
Mary asked the angel, but how could this happen?
I am a virgin.
As I reread this passage this week for probably the 200th time, something jumped off the page at me.
What jumped off the page at me, what I never noticed before and probably should have noticed because I've been taught how to read the Bible and yet sometimes I miss it.
Is that Mary took issue with what the angel said, not because she didn't think God was faithful to fulfill his promises to the nation of Israel.
She very easily could have said, look around at the circumstances of the nation of Israel.
There is no way, shape or form that God is going to actually fulfill the promises that he promised to our ancestors.
But that's not the thing she took issue with.
She didn't take issue with God being faithful to fulfill his promises.
It's almost assumed in her response to the angel that she has a confident expectation that God is going to do the thing that he promised to do for the nation of Israel.
She's just not so sure about how she might be participating in this process.
Notice she doesn't say, look around.
God's not going to send his Messiah.
He's rejected us.
Look at all of our circumstances.
God's not going to send his Messiah.
She doesn't say, there's no way he's going to send his Messiah.
She says, how could this be?
I'm a virgin.
This isn't going to work scientifically.
I might not be the smartest, most influential person in the world, but I know how biology works.
I am a virgin.
And in our culture, the word hope has come to mean something totally different than what it meant to the people of Israel.
You guys have all probably heard this before.
Actually, all four of the words that we're going to talk about throughout the Advent have come to mean something different to us in our culture than they meant to the biblical audience.
In our culture, hope is a word used to describe wishful thinking towards things that are outside of our control.
I hope that it snows on Christmas.
Anybody else have that same hope?
Some of you are like, no way.
I don't want to be shoveling snow when I should be open in presents.
I hope that the commanders make it to the Super Bowl.
Anybody else have that hope?
Well, a three-game losing streak might start to have some of that hope dwindle away.
We have this wishful thinking towards things outside of our control, but hope in the Bible is usually not referring to this type of hope, but more of a confident expectation rooted in the character and promises of God.
Hebrews 10, 23 says this, let us hold tightly without wavering to the hope that we affirm.
What is our hope rooted in?
God can be trusted to keep his promise.
This is biblical hope, a confident expectation in the promises of God.
Romans 4 says this, even when there was no reason for hope, no circumstantial evidence to hope, Abraham, one of the fathers of the nation of Israel, kept hoping, believing that he would become the father of many nations.
Why?
Why did he keep hoping when there was no reason to hope?
He kept hoping because of what God had said to him.
Abraham never wavered in believing God's promise.
He was fully convinced that God can do whatever he promises.
This is biblical hope, a confident expectation that God will keep his promises no matter what our circumstances look like.
And what I would argue from this passage this morning is that I think that Mary very much so had a confident biblical hope in the coming promise of the Messiah.
She doesn't say there's no way the Messiah is going to come.
Look at my circumstances.
She just says, how might I participate in this?
And what I want to do is just imagine for a few minutes the circumstances around Mary's life that could have led her to lose all confident expectation in the promises of God.
Mary is a young Jewish girl, very young, likely.
Many scholars think she's 12 or 13 years old.
A young Jewish girl born into a poor family, living in a podunk town in the middle of nowhere.
A small village called Nazareth.
Later in the Scriptures, someone will ask this question when they're told that Jesus is from Nazareth.
They'll say this.
If you want to know what the culture thought about the place that Mary came from, this poor young girl with challenges all around her, they said, can anything good come from Nazareth?
This is the culture.
This is the experience of Mary.
Not only is she a young, poor girl living in a podunk town in the middle of nowhere.
Mary's people have been crushed under the weight of Roman oppression.
They're essentially at this point living in mandatory slavery with a tax rate of around 80 to 90%.
And on top of all of that, oh yeah.
And remember, remember later in the story, it'll say that they're going to Bethlehem.
Why?
Because Augustus had a Caesar.
Augustus had a, somebody help me.
Census.
Thank you.
He was having a census to figure out how many people were around so that he could probably raise the tax rate.
Okay.
So, I mean, Mary's circumstances all around us.
On top of that, the God who promised to rescue Israel from their oppressors has seemingly been absent from the story of Israel for hundreds of years.
This is the lived experience of Mary, poor, destitute, hopeless for all circumstances around her.
And yet, when the angel shows up and says, the God who promised to send his Messiah is doing it now, she doesn't say there's no way.
She just says, but I'm a virgin.
Isn't that beautiful?
That jumped off the pages of Scripture to me this week.
She had a confident expectation that God would send a Messiah, even though her circumstances would have told her that none of that is true.
She was holding on to a biblical hope in the promises of God.
She just wasn't sure how she might play a part in that role.
With all of the circumstantial evidence stacked against her, she was still seemingly holding on to a confident expectation that God would do what he promised.
I don't think it would be a big leap for me to say that the circumstances Mary is facing is likely as bad, if not worse, than pretty much all of us in this room.
However, I do not want to downplay the suffering of the people in this room.
I know many of you, and I've had many conversations with you, those of you who are suffering right now.
Many of us are suffering, and the holiday season tends to exasperate that suffering, magnifies that emotion.
Many of our worldly hopes have been let down over and over and over again.
The people we expected to stay have left.
The money we expected to have in our account has dwindled.
The regular checkup at the doctor's office turned into an unexpected diagnosis.
Even our hope, even our hope in God to deliver us from the pain is fading away.
Many of us have years and years of unanswered prayers.
These are the experiences of the people of God on a regular basis.
If you can resonate at all with any of Mary's circumstances, you are not alone.
This was her experience, and yet somehow she was holding on to the hope that God would do what he said.
How could Mary possibly have hope in the promises of God in light of her circumstances?
Well, to go back to our illustration of the church calendar, the Jewish people had one of the best religious calendars in all of human history.
Their calendar, their regular weekly, monthly, and yearly rhythms were built around reminding themselves,
regularly reminding themselves of God's faithfulness to their ancestors in the past.
From Noah to Abraham to Moses to David, and on and on we could go, they were constantly looking backward to the promises that God fulfilled through his people.
And they were constantly looking forward to the promises of the Messiah who was to come from the line of David.
This was likely Mary's fuel.
The fuel for Mary's hope was her participation in the Jewish calendar, reminding herself of what God had done for her people in the past,
and looking forward to the promises that he made to them in the future.
And this can become the same fuel for us to experience the type of hope that goes beyond any circumstantial evidence.
With one major, major change.
See, Mary only had Old Testament fulfillments to look back to.
We have the evidence of the empty tomb to look back to.
We live in a privileged position because the things that Mary looked back to in the Jewish experience,
the promises that God fulfilled through Moses and David and all of the ancestors of the faith,
those things were all shadows of the thing to come in Jesus.
We live in a privileged position because the things Mary looked back to were all shadows pointing to God's ultimate redemption plan of Jesus.
And now we get to live in a position where we look back to an empty tomb,
and that gives us confident expectation no matter what our circumstances might be.
We can now look back to the death and resurrection of Jesus,
and because of that confident expectation, look forward to the promises of the second coming.
1 Corinthians 15.
I've got to go fast.
I never think I'm going to have to go as fast as I'm going to have to go until we get here.
Okay.
You guys need to listen faster, okay?
Let's move it on.
Move it on.
All right.
Verse 16.
This is one of the most clear teachings of hope in the New Testament.
And if there is no resurrection of the dead, then Christ has not been raised.
And if Christ has not been raised, if there's no empty tomb, then your faith, this is depressing, but it's the facts.
If Christ has not been raised, your faith is useless and you are still guilty of your sins.
In that case, all who have died believing in Jesus are lost.
And if our hope in Christ is only for this life, we are more to be pitied than anyone in the world.
If you're wasting an hour of your time on a Sunday morning to come in here and sing about a guy who didn't raise from the dead,
you are to be pitied more than anyone else.
But in fact, Christ has been raised from the dead.
He is the first of a great harvest of all who have died.
In one of the New Testament's most in-depth teachings on hope, Paul reminds us that our hope as Christians is rooted in the resurrection of Jesus.
If Jesus hasn't been raised, all we have is wishful thinking about things outside of our control.
That's why people obsess over rooting for bad sports teams.
Because in the difficulty of all of the things they have going on in their life,
they're holding on to hope that the commanders are going to go to the Super Bowl,
because then maybe they'll have a little bit of joy in their life.
If Christ hasn't been raised, all we have is wishful thinking on things outside of our control.
But if Christ has been raised, we have confident expectation that God will do what he said he will do.
Jesus will return and restore all the brokenness of creation.
He will wipe away every tear from our eyes.
Weapons of war will be turned into weapons of farming.
And the earth and all who have bowed their knees to the Prince of Peace will experience the ultimate fulfillment of our hope.
This is why the Christian hope goes beyond any experiential thing that we face.
All of our experiences.
Our hope goes beyond those experiences.
Just like Mary, beyond her experiences of the difficulty of life.
She had a hope.
Because her hope was not rooted in her circumstances.
Her hope was rooted in the character and promises of God.
Hope is the confident expectation that ultimate good will come through the promises of God.
But the thing that I was learning this week is that hope doesn't stop with just confident expectation and the promises of God.
I think God is actually inviting us into not just the confident expectation, but actually participation in the promises of God.
See, Mary had hope that God would send his Messiah.
She just wasn't sure how she fit into the story.
Mary asked the angel, how can this happen?
Because I am a virgin.
A couple things about Mary here in this story that humanizes her.
That makes her a little bit less, or a little bit more relatable.
Mary lacked some crucial biblical knowledge about the promises of God.
Although she's clinging on to the hope that the Messiah would come.
Isaiah 7, 14 clearly says that therefore the Lord himself will give you a sign.
The virgin will conceive and give birth to a son and will call him Emmanuel.
It's the prophecy of God.
And so what I want to point out here is this isn't to shame Mary.
She lived in a culture where women were not educated to the level of men.
She didn't have the opportunity to interact with the specifics of the biblical text.
She had the big picture.
She knew how God had been faithful in the past, but she didn't have the specific biblical knowledge that would allow her to have confidence when angel Gabriel shows up and says,
You're going to birth the Messiah.
And I think what this story points out to us is that God is in the business of using people, not because they've got all the answers, but because they can trust that he does.
And I think many of us in this room, we opt out of the ministry that God is calling us to do because we don't feel qualified.
We don't feel like we know enough.
We don't feel like we have enough of the right information or the right resources to be participants in what God wants to do in and around us.
This is the position that Mary found herself in.
She was confident.
She had a faith and a belief that God was going to do what he said he was going to do,
but she didn't have the knowledge that she needed to know that she could still participate in this.
I was thinking about this this weekend.
You guys, I don't know if I should tell you this or not, but I'm going to because we started it.
So there are multiple people in this congregation who have significantly higher and better biblical education than I do.
And yet week after week, God continues to ask me to come up here and talk about the Bible in front of a number of you who have much higher credentials in biblical education than I do.
Now, what would happen if God, who called me, I have a calling on my life to come up here and to preach God's word.
But what if I had this thought creep into the back of my mind?
I don't know as much as a lot of people that I'm called to preach to.
Well, what would happen is you guys would just find another pastor and everything would be all right.
But I would miss out on doing the thing that God invited me to do because I had doubt about my qualifications or my education.
What I think God wants me to share with you all this morning is that God isn't looking for people who know it all, but for people who are willing to serve and trust that he will provide.
What ministry opportunities might you be missing out on because you think you need to learn more before you do what God's calling you to do?
Not only does she lack a little bit of biblical knowledge, but she lacks confidence in her participation.
Again, Mary seems to be confident that the Messiah will come.
She just isn't sure how she fits into the plan.
I think many of us are in a similar position.
We believe that God can and will do what he promised to do, but we lack the confidence that we have a part to play in God's eternal kingdom coming to earth as it is in heaven.
My big aha moment for this week, every once in a while, usually every week I have some kind of aha moment.
Sometimes it's not until Friday or Saturday, which makes my week a little bit stressful.
But I had this aha moment early in the week that hope is not just a confident expectation, but it is an intentional participation in the promises of God.
Let's continue reading in verse 35.
After Mary asks her very humble and reasonable question, how am I going to birth the Messiah?
I'm a virgin.
The angel replied, the Holy Spirit will come upon you and the power of the Most High will overshadow you.
So the baby to be born will be holy and he will be called the Son of God.
What's more, your relative Elizabeth has become pregnant in her old age.
People used to say that she was barren, but she has conceived a son and is now in her sixth month.
Listen to this, verse 37, for the word of God will never fail.
Mary responded, I am the Lord's servant.
May everything you have said about me come true.
Mary had one humble, reasonable question.
And the Lord is kind and gracious to answer that question.
He says, the Holy Spirit's going to come on you.
He will conceive and you will give birth as a virgin.
And what I want to kind of start to wrap the plane with, Marissa, you can come up.
I did it again.
I'm going to have to.
All right.
Mary is a willing participant in the promises of God, no matter the cost.
After she gets her questions answered, after she has this brief, humble, reasonable interaction with the angel,
she decides that she's going to be a willing participant in the promises of God, no matter the cost.
She would have to have, think about, this isn't just as easy as saying like, okay, I will be the Lord's servant.
Do to me whatever you want to do, and life is good up and to the right for Mary from now on.
Think about the difficult circumstances that Mary's going to have to face moving forward.
She'd have to have some awkward conversations with Joseph, the person that she's legally engaged to be married to.
Engagement's slightly different in that culture than in our culture.
There was a contract that has been signed, and that contract was contingent on her remaining a virgin until the point that she was married.
Going to Joseph and Joseph's parents and convincing them that, no, I am still a virgin.
God just decided to put his child in me.
Slightly awkward, difficult, challenging circumstances.
Not only that, she'd likely experience, think about living in a podunk town in the middle of nowhere with not a whole lot going on.
She'd likely experience the shame-filled gossip of people that she thought were her friends.
Anybody in here had that experience?
Not to mention the cost of, in her mind at this moment, assuming Joseph's going to leave her, she's saying yes to raising a child on her own.
A poor girl from a farm village in the middle of nowhere.
Mary's a willing participant in the promises of God.
Her confident expectation in the character and promises of God led her to be willing, to be obedient to this difficult invitation of God.
Anybody ever, anybody in here ever got a difficult invitation from God?
God's typically not in the business of inviting us to do something that's easy.
And yet, because of her confident expectation in the promises and character of God, she was a willing participant.
So I said, I hoped by the end of this that you would see Mary as a slightly more relatable character than just this famous person from a familiar passage.
You, like Mary, have been offered the presence of the Holy Spirit.
The same Spirit that rose Jesus from the grave, the same Spirit that conceived Jesus in Mary's virgin womb, is living inside of each of us who have trusted in Christ.
Like Mary, we have been invited to participate in God's plan of bringing heaven to earth.
Ephesians 2, verse 10 says that you are God's workmanship, created in Christ Jesus to do good works, which he prepared in advance for me to do, us to do, you to do.
Like Mary, we've been offered the Holy Spirit and invited to participate in the promises of God.
Like Mary, many of us in this room are experiencing difficult circumstances that might cause us to lose hope in God altogether.
That's you, if you're in here and you're just clinging on to your last strand of hope.
I empathize with you.
And I really don't have, from stage, much to give you.
We could sit down, we could have a face-to-face conversation with some more nuance, but ultimately, as a pastor, all I have to give you is what Paul gave the Corinthians, and that is the vision of the empty tomb.
If Jesus truly raised from the dead, then no matter your earthly circumstances, and whether or not God answers the prayers that you've been praying for years and years and years or not, you can have a hope that goes beyond this life into eternity.
My wife came back from a conference, and she got a hat, cool merch.
Can't go to a conference without cool merch.
The hat's been hanging in our bedroom, and I walk by it every once in a while, and the hat says,
If it's not good, God's not done.
If you're in here, and you're struggling with everything inside of you to hold on to hope, if it's not good, God's not done.
And that might not mean this earth.
And that's where we've got to be real in our preaching, authentic in our preaching.
I hear a lot of pastors who talk about, if it's not good, God's not done, and he's promising you that God's going to show up in your circumstance and fix everything.
That might not be the case, this side of death.
But it will be the case when Christ returns.
That passage in 1 Corinthians 15, another thing that stuck out to me this week, talked about Christ being the first fruits of the resurrection.
I'm not a farmer.
Some of you are.
You know the experience of the first fruit.
And I was thinking about that.
Again, not a farmer.
So if I butcher this, I'm really sorry.
I asked some farming friends, and they seemed to confirm it.
But my understanding is, you plant a seed in the ground, and the seed has to die for the plant to grow.
Jesus went into the tomb dead as a doornail.
Not kind of alive, not in a coma, dead.
He rose again three days later to prove that he was who he said he was, and that we can have a confident expectation in him to fulfill his future promises, no matter the circumstances that we might face.
So if you're in here and you're struggling to hold on to hope, like Mary looked back to the promises of God from Moses to David and onward, we can look back to the empty tomb and remind ourselves that if it's not good, God's not done.
Like Mary, we might feel the lack of confidence to be used by God.
But like Mary, we've been offered the power of the Holy Spirit.
We've been invited to participate in the promises of God.
So will we respond like Mary?
Let it be done to me as you have said.
I am the Lord's servant.
Will we step into confident expectation of God to use us to do exceedingly abundantly more than we could ever ask, think, or imagine?
Or will we sit it out on the sidelines and let other people participate in what God wants us to do?
Hope is the confident expectation and intentional participation in the promises of God until he returns.
Let's pray.
Father, God, I know there are a number of us that are all over the spectrum when it comes to biblical hope.
I pray your Holy Spirit today would speak truth to each one of us.
Let us hear what we need to hear.
Let us believe in what we need to believe in and let us have perseverance.
Let us be encouraged by the story of Mary, a poor farm girl from the middle of nowhere.
God, may we see her story in her story of faith that we can learn from, that we can experience ourself as we receive the gift of the Holy Spirit and say yes to the invitation of God in our lives.
God, may we be a church that gets to see you do incredible things through ordinary people just saying yes to whatever it is you're asking them to do.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
I'd love for you to stand up as we dismiss.
I'm going to read a prayer of hope over each one of us.
Church, may the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace as you trust in him so that you may overflow with hope by the power of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.
Go in peace.
Thank you.